What part of the audio signal is really important for recognizing speech?
哪部分音频信号对语音识别最重要？
One human creates words and another human hears them.
一个人说 另一个人听
Our speech is constrained by
我们说的话会受
both our voice-making mechanisms and what we can perceive with our ears.
发声系统和耳朵接收能力的限制
Let's start with the ear and the pitches we can hear.
我们先讲耳朵和人类可接收的音高
The Mel Scale was developed in 1937
梅尔刻度于 1937 年提出
and tells us what pitches human listeners can truly discern.
描述了人类可真正识别的音高
It turns out that some frequencies sound the same to us but we
其实 有些频率我们听起来并无不同
hear differences in lower frequencies more distinctly than in higher frequencies.
但对我们来说 低频的差异要比高频的明显
If we can't hear a pitch,
如果是我们听不到的音高
there is no need to include it in our data,
那就没必要保留在数据里了
and if our ear can't distinguish two different frequencies,
如果人耳无法分辨两种不同的频率
then they might as well be considered the same for our purposes.
那为我们便利 就可以把这两种视为相同的频率
For the purposes of feature extraction,
为了进行特征提取
we can put the frequencies of the spectrogram into bins that are
我们可以给频谱图的频率分组
relevant to our own ears and filter out sound that we can't hear.
分组依据与人耳接收能力有关 这样就能过滤我们听不见的声音
This reduces the number of frequencies we're looking at by quite a bit.
从而大幅减少我们要处理的频率数
That's not the end of the story though.
而这还不够
We also need to separate the elements of sound that are speaker-independent.
我们还得把不受讲者影响的声音元素分离出来
For this, we focus on the voice-making mechanism we use to create speech.
为此 我们来看看人类说话用的发声系统
Human voices vary from person to person
人的嗓音各不相同
even though our basic anatomy features are the same.
哪怕人体基本解剖特征是一样的
We can think of a human voice production model as a combination of source and filter,
我们可以把人声生成模型想成是声源和过滤器的组合体
where the source is unique to an individual and the filter
每个人的声源都不同
is the articulation of words that we all use when speaking.
过滤器则是我们说话都会用到的单词发音
Cepstral analysis relies on this model for separating the two.
倒谱分析就靠这个模型来区分这两者
The cepstrum can be extracted from
我们可以用算法将倒谱
a signal with an algorithm you'll find in the references.
从信号中提取出来 具体算法请见参考部分
The main thing to remember is that we're dropping the component of speech unique to
你要记住的关键点是 我们要舍弃带有个体声带特征的语音成分
individual vocal chords and preserving the shape of the sound made by the vocal tract.
保留声道形成的那部分声音形状
Cepstral analysis combined with mel frequency analysis get you
将倒谱分析与梅尔频率分析相结合
12 or 13 MFCC features related to speech.
你就能得到与语音有关的 12 或 13 种 MFCC (梅尔频率倒谱系数) 特征
Delta and Delta-Delta MFCC features can optionally be appended to the feature set.
你还可选择是否要在特征集里附加 Δ 和 ΔΔ MFCC 特征
This will double or triple the number of features
虽然附加特征会使特征数增加一倍或两倍
but has been shown to give better results in ASR.
但事实证明 这样 ASR 的效果更好
The takeaway for using MFCC feature extraction is that we greatly reduce
使用 MFCC 特征提取的好处就是
the dimensionality of our data and at the same time we squeeze noise out of the system.
我们不仅能大幅减少数据维数 还能过滤掉系统噪声
Next, we'll look at sound from a language perspective,
接下来 我们将从语言的角度来研究声音
the phonetics of the words we hear.
讲讲单词语音学